<Chapter Label="backtracking">
  <Heading>Backtracking</Heading>

<P/>Backtracking is an algorithmic technique for searching in
combinatorial spaces: For instance, when you need to find a particular
function (morphism, coloring, etc) subject to some criterion
(<E>iso</E>morphism, <E>proper</E> coloring, etc).

<P/>In this chapter we describe the technique and
the facilities provided by &YAGS; to aid in the rapid prototyping of
backtracking algorithms. This chapter is written for the non-expert
programmer, which is who can benefit the most from these facilities.

<P/>While the expert programmers will not have any problem designing
their own backtracking algorithms, they can still benefit from &YAGS;'s
backtracking facilities since it may still be faster to
implement/test/prototype a backtracking algorithm using &YAGS;'s
facilities. We recommend the expert programmer to go directly to
<Ref Func="Backtrack"/> where a minimal non-trivial example (for
computing derangements) is shown.

<P/>The kind of combinatorial problems that can be addressed by
backtracking are those that can be represented by a decision tree:
those where we have to make a succession of choices to find a solution.
These include problems where we want to find: morphisms,
isomorphisms, cages, colorings, cliques, Hamiltonian cycles, walks,
paths, subgraphs, and much much more.  Combinatorial problems that can
be represented by a decision tree are truly everywhere.
&YAGS; backtracking facilities are provided by means of the
operations <C>BacktrackBag(Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C> and
<C>Backtrack(L,Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C>.

<Section Label="simplestexamples">
  <Heading>Simplest Examples: Using <C>Opts</C> and <C>Done</C></Heading>
  
<P/>As a concrete example consider graph colorings: You
have a set of colors, say  <C>["red", "blue"]</C> and a graph, say
<C>g:=PathGraph(3)</C>, whose vertices are <C>[1, 2, 3]</C>.  Then a
coloring is a function <M>f: \{1, 2, 3\} \rightarrow \{red,
blue\}</M>, which in &YAGS; would be represented by a List <C>L:=[
f(1), f(2), f(3)]</C>. There are (obviously) eight of such colorings,
which are easy to list using <C>BacTrackBag(Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C>:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> colors:=["red","green"];
[ "red", "green" ]
gap> BacktrackBag(colors,ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ [ "red", "red", "red" ], [ "red", "red", "green" ], 
  [ "red", "green", "red" ], [ "red", "green", "green" ], 
  [ "green", "red", "red" ], [ "green", "red", "green" ], 
  [ "green", "green", "red" ], [ "green", "green", "green" ] ]
gap> Length(last);
8
</Example>

<P/>In the previous example, only two parameters of
<C>BacktrackBag</C> are really used, namely: <C>Opts</C> (which stands
for <E>options</E>) and <C>Done</C>; when used in this way, <C>Opts</C>
is simply the codomain of the sought function and <C>Done</C> is
simply the size of the domain. When working with graph colorings it is
common to use numbers instead of actual colors or color names, so we
could also write even more compactly:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ [ 0, 0, 0 ], [ 0, 0, 1 ], [ 0, 1, 0 ], [ 0, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 0, 0 ], 
  [ 1, 0, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ]
</Example>

<P/>Sometimes you just want a few solutions and not the whole
bag. This is specially true when the bag is too huge (which is often
the case since the bag tend to grow exponentially in
the size of the domain). For these cases, we have
<C>Backtrack(L,Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C>:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> L:=[]; 
[  ]
gap> Backtrack(L,[0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ 0, 0, 0 ]
gap> L;
[ 0, 0, 0 ]
gap> Backtrack(L,[0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ 0, 0, 1 ]
gap> L;                                 
[ 0, 0, 1 ]
gap> L:=[1,1,0];
[ 1, 1, 0 ]
gap> Backtrack(L,[0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ 1, 1, 1 ]
gap> L;                                 
[ 1, 1, 1 ]
gap> Backtrack(L,[0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
fail
gap> L;
[ fail ]
</Example>

<P/><C>Backtrack(L,Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C> returns one solution at a
time and it also stores the solution within <C>L</C>, so that <C>L</C>
can be used as a starting point for the search of the next
solution. Usually, <C>L:=[]</C> is used for the first search. When
Calling <C>Backtrack(L,Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C>, <C>L</C> may also
contain a <E>partial</E> solution (i.e. a prefix of a solution like
<C>L:=[ 1 ]</C> or <C>L:=[ 1, 0 ]</C>), however it will trust the user
on this and it will not check that <C>L</C> is indeed a partial
solution.

<P/><C>Backtrack</C> returns <C>fail</C> when no more solutions are
available, but for technical reasons, <C>L</C> must always be a list,
so <C>L:=[ fail ]</C> is the final value of <C>L</C>.

<P/>Now, so far, the graph itself have not been used and the
parameters <C>Chk</C> and <C>Extra</C> have not been explained. Both
issues are addressed in the next section.

  </Section>
  <Section Label="fullexamples">
    <Heading>Full Examples: Using <C>Chk</C> and <C>Extra</C></Heading>

<P/>In graph theory we are usually more interested in <E>proper
colorings</E> than just in colorings. A proper coloring is a coloring
in which no two adjacent vertices have the same color. We can easily
accommodate the new requirement within our backtracking operations.  We
are going to use <C>Chk</C> to check the fulfillment of the condition
at each step in the construction of a solution. Moreover, in order to
check the new condition we certainly need the extra information
contained in the graph we are coloring. This extra information (the graph) is
passed in the <C>Extra</C> parameter.

<P/>More generally, <C>Chk</C> is a user-provided function
<C>Chk(L,Extra)</C> which receives a partial solution <C>L</C> and
some extra information <C>Extra</C>; it returns <C>false</C> whenever
it knows that <C>L</C> can not be completed to a full solution and it
returns <C>true</C> otherwise. Note then that our backtracking
operations internally call <C>Chk</C> several times during the process
of constructing each solution: once each time <C>L</C> grows in
length. In each call to <C>Chk</C> it is safe to assume that all
proper prefixes of <C>L</C> have already been verified and approved by
<C>Chk</C>. 

<P/>In our example, <C>L</C> contains the color choices already made
for the first vertices: <C>1, 2, ... Length(L)</C>. It is safe to
assume that all but the last choice are already checked to satisfy the
properness requirement. The last color choice so far is then the one
in <C>L[Length(L)]</C> and we have to check (within <C>Chk</C>) if it
also satisfy the properness requirement. We can do it like this:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> g:=PathGraph(3);;                                    
gap> chk:=function(L,g)                                   
>        local x,y;                                           
>        if L=[] then return true; fi;                        
>        x:=Length(L);                                        
>        for y in [1..x-1] do                                 
>           if IsEdge(g,[x,y]) and L[x]=L[y] then
>              return false;
>           fi;
>        od;
>        return true;
>    end;
function( L, g ) ... end
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],chk,Order(g),g);                     
[ [ 0, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 0, 1 ] ]
</Example>

<P/>Now we get only two solutions, as expected. We emphasize here the
fact that <C>Chk</C> is internally called by <C>BacktrackBag</C> each
time <C>L</C> grows in length.  Therefore (for instance) at some point
the partial solution <C>[ 0, 0 ]</C> is tried and since it is found
unfeasible by <C>Chk</C> is is discarded and no other partial solution
with that prefix is ever tried. This produces huge reductions in
execution time as compared to the (naive) approach of computing all the
colorings first and then filtering out those which does not satisfy
the properness requirement. In particular we can compute proper
colorings for graphs where the naive approach fails:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> g:=PathGraph(70);;
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],chk,Order(g),g);
[ [ 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 
      0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 
      1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 
      0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1 ], 
  [ 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 
      1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 
      0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 
      1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0 ] ]
</Example>

<P/>Of course, we can now compute colorings for many other graphs as well:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> g:=CycleGraph(5);;                 
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],chk,Order(g),g);
[  ]
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1,2],chk,Order(g),g);
[ [ 0, 1, 0, 1, 2 ], [ 0, 1, 0, 2, 1 ], [ 0, 1, 2, 0, 1 ], 
  [ 0, 1, 2, 0, 2 ], [ 0, 1, 2, 1, 2 ], [ 0, 2, 0, 1, 2 ], 
  [ 0, 2, 0, 2, 1 ], [ 0, 2, 1, 0, 1 ], [ 0, 2, 1, 0, 2 ], 
  [ 0, 2, 1, 2, 1 ], [ 1, 0, 1, 0, 2 ], [ 1, 0, 1, 2, 0 ], 
  [ 1, 0, 2, 0, 2 ], [ 1, 0, 2, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 0, 2, 1, 2 ], 
  [ 1, 2, 0, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 2, 0, 1, 2 ], [ 1, 2, 0, 2, 0 ], 
  [ 1, 2, 1, 0, 2 ], [ 1, 2, 1, 2, 0 ], [ 2, 0, 1, 0, 1 ], 
  [ 2, 0, 1, 2, 0 ], [ 2, 0, 1, 2, 1 ], [ 2, 0, 2, 0, 1 ], 
  [ 2, 0, 2, 1, 0 ], [ 2, 1, 0, 1, 0 ], [ 2, 1, 0, 2, 0 ], 
  [ 2, 1, 0, 2, 1 ], [ 2, 1, 2, 0, 1 ], [ 2, 1, 2, 1, 0 ] ]
gap> g:=Icosahedron;;                          
gap> Backtrack([],[0,1,2],chk,Order(g),g);
fail
gap> Backtrack([],[0,1,2,3],chk,Order(g),g);
[ 0, 1, 2, 1, 2, 3, 3, 0, 2, 3, 0, 1 ]
</Example>


  </Section>
  <Section Label="advancedexamples">
    <Heading>Advanced Examples: When <C>Opts</C> and <C>Done</C> are functions</Heading>

<P/>Our backtracking operations <C>BacktrackBag(Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C> and
<C>Backtrack(L,Opts,Chk,Done,Extra)</C> are even more flexible that shown so far.
In our previous examples <C>Opts</C> was always a list and <C>Done</C>
was always an integer. Both can also be functions.

<P/>When <C>Opts</C> is a function, it receives <C>L</C> and
<C>Extra</C>, and then <C>Opts(L,Extra)</C> should return the list of
options available to extend the partial solution <C>L</C> at that
particular stage.  This way the list of options can be different at
different times which is useful for instance when the union of all
possible options is too big or even unbounded.

<P/>When <C>Done</C> is a function, it also receives <C>L</C> and
<C>Extra</C>, and then <C>Done(L,Extra)</C> returns <C>true</C>
whenever <C>L</C> is a full solution and it returns <C>false</C>
otherwise. This is useful when not all the solutions have the same
length. Thus the number <C>N</C> we used to put in place of the
function <C>Done(L,Extra)</C> is equivalent to the function
<C>Done:=function(L,Extra) return Length(L) >= N; end;</C>. 

<P/>Also, when a number <C>N</C> is used in place of <C>Done</C>, an
implicit upper bound <C>Length(L)&lt;= N</C> is added internally to
<C>Chk</C>, so it is <E>imperative</E> to add such an explicit bound to
<C>Chk</C> when a function is used for <C>Done</C> otherwise the
backtracking algorithm will try to find longer and longer solutions
without bound or end until the memory of the computer is exhausted.

<P/>As an example, assume we want to find all the walks on 5-cycle that
start at vertex 1 and end at vertex 2 with length at most 4 (at most 5
vertices). Then we can proceed as follows:

<P/>
<Example>
gap> g:=CycleGraph(5);
Graph( Category := SimpleGraphs, Order := 5, Size := 
5, Adjacencies := [ [ 2, 5 ], [ 1, 3 ], [ 2, 4 ], [ 3, 5 ], [ 1, 4 ] 
 ] )
gap> opts:=function(L,g) 
>             if L=[] then 
>                return [1]; 
>             else 
>                return Adjacency(g,L[Length(L)]); 
>            fi; 
>    end;
function( L, g ) ... end
gap> chk:=function(L,g) return Length(L)&lt;= 5; end;
function( L, g ) ... end
gap> done:=function(L,g) return L[Length(L)]=2; end;
function( L, g ) ... end
gap> BacktrackBag(opts,chk,done,g);
[ [ 1, 2 ], [ 1, 2, 1, 2 ], [ 1, 2, 3, 2 ], [ 1, 5, 1, 2 ], 
  [ 1, 5, 4, 3, 2 ] ]
</Example>

<P/>Finally you may wonder why only <E>one</E> extra parameter
<C>Extra</C> is allowed, what if I need more than one? Well, the
parameter <C>Extra</C> may be any object supported by &GAP;; indeed
&YAGS; only uses it to pass information to the user-defined functions
<C>Opts(L,Extra)</C>, <C>Chk(L,Extra)</C> and <C>Done(L,Extra)</C>.
Hence, if you need pass more than one extra parameter, say two graphs
<C>g</C> and <C>h</C>, you just put them in a list (or record, etc)
and pass the parameter <C>Extra:=[g,h]</C>.

  </Section>
  <Section Label="debuggingbacktracks">
    <Heading>Debugging Backtracking Algorithms.</Heading>

  <P/>Sooner or later you will need to debug a bactracking algorithm
  that is not working as expected, or at least, you would like to know
  how much work your algorithm has done and how much remains to be
  done to decide if it is worth waiting for an answer (since
  backtraking techniques easily produce algorithms which may take eons
  to finish).

  <P/>All of &YAGS;'s backtracking operations report progress info at
  <C>InfoLevel</C> 3 to &YAGS;'s info class <C>YAGSInfo.InfoClass</C>
  (see <Ref Label="YAGSInfo.InfoClass"/>). In short, this means that setting
  <C>SetInfoLevel(YAGSInfo.InfoClass,3);</C> will cause all
  backtraking operations to report progress information to the console
  (may be redirected to a file by setting the undocumented variable
  <C>YAGSInfo.InfoOutput</C> accordingly): The contents of <C>L</C>
  will be reported each time it grows in length. Revert to de default
  behavior by setting the infolevel to 0 using
  <C>SetInfoLevel(YAGSInfo.InfoClass,0);</C>

<P/>
<Log>
gap> SetInfoLevel(YAGSInfo.InfoClass,3); 
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
#I [  ]
#I [ 0 ]
#I [ 0, 0 ]
#I [ 0, 0, 0 ]
#I [ 0, 0, 1 ]
#I [ 0, 1 ]
#I [ 0, 1, 0 ]
#I [ 0, 1, 1 ]
#I [ 1 ]
#I [ 1, 0 ]
#I [ 1, 0, 0 ]
#I [ 1, 0, 1 ]
#I [ 1, 1 ]
#I [ 1, 1, 0 ]
#I [ 1, 1, 1 ]
[ [ 0, 0, 0 ], [ 0, 0, 1 ], [ 0, 1, 0 ], [ 0, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 0, 0 ], 
[ 1, 0, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ]
gap> SetInfoLevel(YAGSInfo.InfoClass,0);
gap> BacktrackBag([0,1],ReturnTrue,3,[]);
[ [ 0, 0, 0 ], [ 0, 0, 1 ], [ 0, 1, 0 ], [ 0, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 0, 0 ], 
  [ 1, 0, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 0 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ]
</Log>

  <P/>The same progress report info apply to all &YAGS; functions that
  internally use <Ref Func="Backtrack"/> or <Ref
  Func="BacktrackBag"/>, namely <Ref Func="CompletesOfGivenOrder"/>,
  <Ref Func="Orientations"/> and all morphism-related operations in
  Chapter <Ref Chap="morphismsofgraphs"/>.
  
  </Section>
</Chapter>
