<Chapter Label="preface">
  <Heading>Preface</Heading>

  <Section Label="disclaimer">
    <Heading>Disclaimer</Heading>
    <P/><B>This is not an official release yet</B>, this is a version in development. 
    This particular version, 0.0.1, changes from one day to another without warning 
    and even without a change in the version number. Also, the operations and 
    global variables can still change name or even disappear without warning. 
    No commitment is made at the moment concerning compatibility of this version of 
    the software with any future version.

    <P/>As of this writing (16/Feb/2016) there are only two trustworthy chapters in this manual: 
    Appendixes <Ref Appendix="alltopic" Style="Text"/> and 
    <Ref Appendix="allalpha" Style="Text"/>; also the file 
    <F>cheatsheet-yags.pdf</F> (within directory: <F>YAGSDIR/doc/</F>) may be useful. 
    All other chapters may contain errors, broken links and misleading information 
    (with higher probability).

    <P/>The first official version will be 0.0.2 and is scheduled to be ready this year (2016), 
    so come back soon.
  </Section>

  <Section Label="welcometoyags">
    <Heading>Welcome to &YAGS;</Heading>
    <P/>&YAGS; - <E>Yet Another Graph System</E> is a &GAP; package for dealing with 
    graphs, in the sense of Graph Theory (not bar graphs, pie charts nor graphs of functions). 
    Our graphs are then, ordered pairs <M>G=(V,E)</M>, where 
    <M>V</M> is a finite set of vertices and <M>E</M> is a finite set of edges which are 
    (ordered or unordered) pairs of vertices.

    <P/>&YAGS; was initiated by M.A. Pizaña in May 2003, and soon incorporated 
    the work of R. MacKinney-Romero and R. Villarroel-Flores. It sprang from our need of
    computing graphs and graph parameters within our research on graph theory and
    clique graphs. Consequently, &YAGS; is well suited for these purposes.

    <P/>&YAGS; is a &GAP; package and hence its code is interpreted and not compiled
    (although some compilation possibilities exist in &GAP;). Therefore, from the very beginning,
    it was clear that speed is not our main goal. Instead, we wanted a very functional, full-featured
    system; a system adequate for rapid prototyping of algorithms; and a quick,  easy-to-use, way for
    testing the rapidly changing working conjectures that are typical of the research process.

    <P/>Over the years, &YAGS; grew to its present size of more than 200 methods and more
    than 8 thousands lines of code. We considered that all this code and effort could
    (and should) be useful for other people and then we decided to engaged in the task of
    tying up loose ends and writing this manual.

    <P/>We would like to mention that we started using <Package>GRAPE</Package>, and we are grateful with
    its author, Leonard H. Soicher, for the very useful system that we used for several years.
    But at some point we needed some Object-Oriented features that were not easy to
    implement in <Package>GRAPE</Package> and our own subsystem had to follow its own way.
    If the reader has a profound need for having groups acting on her/his graphs, then
    <Package>GRAPE</Package> may be the best choice. On the other hand, &YAGS; offers
    a much wider set of functions (Appendix <Ref Appendix="allalpha"/>);
    a graph-drawing subsystem (<Ref Func="Draw"/>);
    many methods for dealing with graph homomorphism (Chapter <Ref Chap="morphismsofgraphs"/>);
    an Object-Oriented approach that simplifies the task of working with several
    different graph categories (Chapter <Ref Chap="graphcategories"/>);
    and a generic backtracking subsystem useful to solve many combinatorial problems easily
    (Chapter <Ref Chap="backtracking"/>).
  </Section>

  <Section Label="citingyags">
    <Heading>Citing &YAGS;</Heading>
    <P/>If you publish a result and you used &YAGS; during your research, please cite
    us as you would normally do with a research paper:<Br/><Br/>

    R. MacKinney-Romero, M.A. Pizaña and R. Villarroel-Flores.<Br/>
    <E>YAGS - Yet Another Graph System, Version &VERSION;</E> (&RELEASEYEAR;)<Br/>
    <URL>http://xamanek.izt.uam.mx/yags/</URL><Br/><Br/>

    <Code>
      @manual{YAGS,
      author = {R. MacKinney-Romero and M.A. Pizaña and R. Villarroel-Flores},
      title = {YAGS - Yet Another Graph System, Version &VERSION;},
      year = {&RELEASEYEAR;},
      note = {http://xamanek.izt.uam.mx/yags/},
      }
    </Code><Br/><Br/>

    Also, if you install &YAGS; we will very happy to know about it, so please contribute to increase
    world's happiness by sending us a notification to: <Email>yags@xamanek.izt.uam.mx</Email>. 
  </Section>

  <Section Label="authors">
    <Heading>Authors</Heading>
    <P/>The authors of &YAGS; in the chronological order of their first contribution 
    are as follows:<Br/><Br/>

    M.A. Pizaña<Br/>
    Departamento de Ingeniería Eléctrica<Br/>
    Universidad Autónoma Metropolitana<Br/>
    <Email>map@xanum.uam.mx</Email><Br/><Br/>

    R. MacKinney-Romero<Br/>
    Departamento de Ingeniería Eléctrica<Br/>
    Universidad Autónoma Metropolitana<Br/>
    <Email>rene@xanum.uam.mx</Email><Br/><Br/>

    R. Villarroel-Flores<Br/>
    Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas<Br/>
    Universidad Autónoma del Estado de Hidalgo<Br/>
    <Email>rafaelv@uaeh.edu.mx</Email>
  </Section>

  <Section Label="moreinformation">
    <Heading>More Information</Heading>
    <P/>More information about &YAGS; can be found on its official web page: <URL>http://xamanek.izt.uam.mx/yags/</URL>

    <P/>You can receive notifications about &YAGS; (i.e. new releases, bug fixes, etc.) by
    subscribing to its email distribution list: <URL>http://xamanek.izt.uam.mx/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/yagsnews/</URL>

    <P/>If you are a developer, you may contribute to our project on our public repository: <URL>https://github.com/yags/main/</URL>

    <P/>Comments, support requests, bug reports and installation notifications are
    welcome at <Email>yags@xamanek.izt.uam.mx</Email>.
  </Section>
</Chapter>
